我们的人数增长之快 远远超过预料
Our numbers have grown beyond wildest expectation.
问题是凛冬将至
And winter will soon be upon us.
如此乱局 元老院已经力不从心了
Resources of the Senate are drained by these conflicts.
有一个人
There is one among us
可以自掏腰包支援前线
who could fund endeavor from his own purse.
要养这么庞大的军队
It would take considerable coin and effort
财力精力可不少
to raise such a force.
作为回报 你可以有指挥权
And in return you will be offered a command,
位次当然在科西尼斯和费尤瑞斯之后
under Cossinius and Furius, of course.
我有点后悔当初离开温柔的海风
I begin to question turning from the calm of the ocean breeze,
还有希留爱沙山城墙的庇护了
and the safety of my city's walls in Sinuessa en Valle.
我同意他们的条件
Their terms are agreeable.
父亲
Father.
斯巴达克斯 这个人身上有信
Spartacus, this one carried a message.
原来是您计划好的
You planned this.
这上面说 望此消息能
It speaks of hope that word finds them safe
安全抵达宅邸
within the villa.
剿灭斯巴达克斯的大任
Sole command and charge to bring Spartacus
全仰仗你了
to deserved end is now yours.
没有哪座宅子
There isn't a villa in all the land
能容纳这么多人
that could hold such numbers.
的确没有
No, there is not.
要有一座城才能容纳我们
Only a city could hold us now.
《斯巴达克斯：诅咒者之战》
《兵临城下》
这可没有屠马那么容易 对吧
Not as easy as butchering a horse, is it?
它们那一踢可温柔多了
Their kick is considerably more gentle.
迪欧特莫斯
Diotimus.
斯巴达克斯召见你
Spartacus summons you.
南部海岸
The southern coast?
这就迫使克拉苏要找到我们 必须远道行军
It will force Crassus' army to march much greater distance to meet us,
耗尽他们的体力和物资
sapping strength and supplies.
可等我们到那里也只剩一口气了
But will we not stand as drained at journey's end?
我们拿下城池便可以恢复元气
The comfort of city walls will see us revived.
克拉苏没有这优势
A thing denied Crassus.
迪欧特莫斯
Diotimus.
我想听听你的建议
I would have your counsel.
很抱歉
Apologies...
我对战略战术一无所知
I am absent knowledge concerning strategies of war.
不过有的事情你很熟悉
Yet you are well versed in other needs.
你提到过一座有城墙庇护
You spoke of a city protected by walls
海风吹拂的城池
and caressed by ocean's breeze.
希留爱沙山
Ah...Sinuessa en Valle.
我在那里住了很多年
Uh, home to me for many years...
那你一定很清楚那儿的防御体系
Then you know of its defenses.
你想夺下那座城
You would take the city?
至于怎么夺 要看你怎么说了
Mmm, that path rests upon your words.
有两道城门
There are two gates.
主城门朝西 正对着山陵
The main one faces the hills to the west.
白天为贸易往来而开门 日落后便封闭起来
Open for trade during light of day, secured as sun retires.
另一道呢
And the other?
倚悬崖而建
Set against cliffs,
直通往米利亚峰的峡谷
running up to the canyons of Melia Ridge.
冬天无法通行
Impassable during winter months,
现在山顶已经入冬
which are already upon its peak.
我可不希望大家困在那里
I would not find ourselves trapped there.
我也一样
Nor I.
主城门怎么样
How stands the main gate?
一旦封闭 坚不可摧
Formidable, once sealed.
几个人偷偷摸进去 可以趁夜打开城门吗
Could a few men from within see it opened, beneath cover of night?
城门戒备森严 而且你们也没有机会
It is well defended, and you would be absent means.
市政官担心有人拿武器对付卫兵
The Aedile feared weapons could be turned upon the guards,
因此凡搜到的兵器都锁在城门旁的储物室内
ordered all of note locked within a storeroom near the gate.
进城不能带武器吗
We must give up sword upon entering?
还是换个更可行的目标吧
Let us turn toward more favorable prospect.
稍等
Hold a moment...
我旅行时和一个人打过交道
I had dealings with a man during my travels,
他说他就来自那座城
who claimed the city his own.
埃提斯 他是铁匠
Attius, a blacksmith by trade.
我听说过他
I know of him.
我主人经常说很讨厌这家伙
My dominus often spoke of his distaste for the man.
我们能相信罗马人吗
Can we lay trust in the Roman?
他就是有个罗马名字
He stands Roman only by name.
只要给他足够多的钱币
Weigh his purse with enough coin
管你是色雷斯人还是高卢人 有奶便是娘
and he would call Thrace or Gaul his mother.
那么你跟我一起去同他交涉
I would have you with me to break word.
我也去
I would join you.
动身出发
Break camp and follow.
埋伏好 听我号令
Remain unseen until called to purpose.
你的烙印怎么办
What of your brands?
如果进城时被搜身 那努力就白费了
If you are searched at the gate, effort will be short lived.
说得对
A point well made.
我那该死的主人对市政官颇有影响力
My fucking dominus holds sway with the Aedile.
就说你要找洛厄斯做买卖
Speak the name of Laurus towards meeting of trade,
说不定能挡开麻烦事
stand chance of avoiding entanglement.
下一次你见到他 就轮到洛厄斯跪下来
The next you greet him, it will be Laurus who kneels...
管你叫主人了
and calls you master.
往前走
Step forward!
可以了
That will do.
交出武器 有武器吗
Give up weapons. Any weapons?
往前走
Step forward!
到希留爱沙山做什么
State business within Sinuessa en Valle.
做粮食买卖
We come for grain.
再就是看你们这儿有什么乐子
And all the pleasures your city has to offer...
你这是侮辱我
Ah...you insult me.
这么一点儿
By so light a palm.
请接受我沉沉的歉意
Well...allow weighted apology...
我要你的镯子 还有上面的珠宝
I would have your brace, and the jewels upon it.
这是我身上最珍贵的东西
It is most treasured possession at this time.
不能交给别人
I would not part with it.
那就他妈的别想进城
Then turn from fucking gate.
来人
Guards!
如您所愿
As you wish.
请转告洛厄斯
Oh, please inform Laurus that...
他的客人没办法赴约了
his guests will not be able to keep intended meeting, hmmm.
等等
Wait.
交出武器
Ah, give over weapons.
跟他美言几句 说德修斯招待得很周全
And grace ear of the man that Decimus saw you well treated.
谢谢
Gratitude.
我保证到时候你有奖赏可拿
I shall see you well rewarded this day.
我知道你的困难 乌尔比安
I understand your plight, Ulpianus,
可你也要理解我夫君啊
but you must understand my husband's.
西利西亚的瘟疫污染了我们的水源
The Cilicians yet plague our waters
斯巴达克斯又袭击我们的陆地运输
and Spartacus now assaults transport upon land.
粮食的价格…
The cost of grain
高得太离谱了
soars beyond reason.
如果我为了弥补损失 给面包涨价的话
If I raise the price of my bread any further to cover loss,
民众恐怕饶不了我
I-I fear the crowd will turn upon me.
这事交给我夫君处理
A matter to be taken up with my husband.
莱塔 我这么要求不只因为利润
I would not ask if profit were my only concern, Laeta.
我妻子怀孕了
My wife is with child.
我帮你说两句吧
I will broach subject with him.
- 谢谢 - 别谢太早
- Gratitude. - Hold sentiment until it is deserved.
我可不指望他心软
I do not expect him to be moved.
三个第纳尔
Three denarii!
没错 今早的新鲜货
Yeah, fresh this morning!
这就是你提到的那人
This is the one you spoke of?
没错 市政官
It is, Aedile.
自从迪欧特莫斯逃跑后 我不就说过吗
I warned you shackle would not stand warning enough
镣铐的威慑力不够
after Diotimus slipped from grasp.
我现在知道了
Words now heeded.
处死他
See it done.
完事后
And in grim wake,
贴出告示 以儆效尤
post notice to quell further unpleasantness.
这边
This way!
站起来
Stand up!
快过来
Come on.
恩尼乌斯
Ennius.
你怎么不去粮仓
Why are you not at the horreum?
让乌尔比安的事情耽搁了
I was delayed by young Ulpianus.
- 他恳请我跟你说… - 现在不是时候
- He has implored me to broach - Now is place nor time.
快点 过去
Come on, get on with it!
受尊敬的市政官大人许可
By permission of honored Aedile,
我向各位说明 又有一个奴隶
I present yet another beloved slave
因大逆不道的思想和图谋叛乱的言行而堕落
fallen to treacherous thought and whisper of rebellion.
摊上这么个恶毒的主 谁能不反
And who would not fall to such beneath heel of a toad?
有人发现他私藏食物
He was discovered secreting scraps of food
打算离开本城 远走高飞
intended for journey far from these walls.
家狗发疯 这不能怪洛厄斯
Laurus cannot be faulted for a dog turned to madness.
善待动物
Show an animal kindness
它们便绝对忠诚于你
and it will give loyalty until the heavens fall.
他打算投奔亲人
A journey that would lead to kinship
只是鞭打它们
Show it nothing but the lash
跟那些意图不轨 叛国作乱的人鬼混
with like mind of untold mischief towards the Republic...
那就难怪它们龇牙了
and wonder not why it bears teeth.
只用镣铐根本就没有什么威慑力了
Shackles alone no longer offer fair deterrent.
必须加上石头以示警醒
Let us add to them with warning of weighted stone
让胆敢有这种念头的人知道 这是死路一条
and the promise of death for any who dare follow in such regard.
站住 听好了
Stop, and listen!
让他尝尝苦头
Make him suffer!
干掉这混蛋
Finish that fucker!
我们要想办法阻止
Must make attempt to end this.
那我们就跟他一个下场了
It would but pair our fate with his.
那人命悬一线 我不能袖手旁观
I will not stand idle while the man's life holds in the balance
斯巴达克斯
Spartacus!
他一定会把你该死的共和国打得血肉横飞
He will see your fucking Republic to blood and shit!
斯巴达克斯
Spartacus!
- 斯巴达克斯 - 要他的脏嘴再也说不出话
- Spartacus! - See rebellious tongue forever stilled!
斯巴达克斯
Spartacus!
去死吧
Die!
等斯巴达克斯把你们统统送进地狱
With Spartacus sent you all to afterlife!
快来啊
Come on!
扔啊
Throw!
报应的时刻到了
This is your time for retribution!
去死吧
Die!
继续扔
Throw more!
好样的 去死
Yeah! Die!
好样的
Yeah!
快来啊 扔
Come on, throw!
你引起他们注意了
You draw attention.
我帮他早些了断
I but end suffering.
我要同样对待那些遭受罗马荼毒的人
As I would for all so afflicted by festering disease of Rome.
每个百人团指派一名号令官
Procure a cornicen for each centuria.
打仗时要确保我的命令清晰无误地传达
I would not have command obscured during battle.
传令官增加三倍
And see tesserarius tripled in number.
如果斯巴达克斯发动夜袭
Watch must be alert should Spartacus attack
必须及时通报
under cover of darkness.
我绝不能像科西尼斯和费尤瑞斯那样措手不及
I will not be caught unawares as Cossinius and Furius.
梅泰勒斯元老又来信了
Another message from Senator Metellus.
他这是要拿羊皮纸压死我们吗
The man threatens to bury us beneath a storm of parchment.
元老院等不及要我们军队
The Senate grows anxious for our troops to move
离开战神广场 追捕斯巴达克斯了
from Field of Mars in pursuit of Spartacus.
不只他们这么急
They are not alone in such thought.
不过还有事情没办完
Mmm, there are yet needs to be attended.
武器装备方面怎么样了
How stand we on account of arma?
萨比努斯和我按要求置备齐了
Sabinus and I have procured what was requested.
您一定会满意
You will be well pleased.
那就掂量掂量你的成果
Let us weigh the worth of your labor,
再考虑你的回报
set achievement to scale.
你已经超出他的预期了
You have exceeded expectation.
他肯定能看到你的价值
He will recognize value of all your efforts.
你最有资格成为仅次于他的指挥官
And who most deserves highest command beneath him.
锻造之神都打不出
Vulcan himself could not have forged
更高贵更精良的武器了
more glorious arma towards noble cause.
确实罕见 你这锻造的技巧
It's a rare thing... for such blasphemy
配得上这渎神的言论
to be proven in execution of skill.
承蒙克拉苏赞赏
I stand humbled by the praise of Crassus.
直说吧 你要价多少
A straighten back, and see words follow towards honest price.
九十第纳尔
Ninety denarii.
最低价格了
My-my finest offering.
稍差一些的价格呢
And cost of less divine spectacle?
士兵的全套装备只要一百二十第纳尔
One hundred and twenty denarii per soldier, fully equipped.
您儿子已经同意了
As agreed upon by your noble son.
价格很公道
A fair price.
打扰了 主人
Apologies, Dominus.
他来了
He has arrived.
你的条件可以接受
Your terms are agreeable.
就由提比略代我完成这笔交易
Tiberius will conclude our business.
好的 谢谢
Yes, of course, gratitude
我没说错吧
Did I not tell you?
不用担心你应有的头衔了
There now stands nothing between you and deserved title.
我他妈的要在这儿耗一整天吗
Am I to be kept waiting entire fucking day?
这要决定于我的夫君
If that is my husband's wish.
那他便要失望了
Well, one he shall not see granted.
恺撒
Caesar!
你的下人忘了自己的身份
Your men forget themselves.
失去理智的人是你
You are the one that has lost mind.
退下
Leave us.
她向来不喜欢我
She never did care for me.
她有什么理由喜欢你呢
Have you ever given her reason?
没把她当女神膜拜是我的错
My apologies for not worshipping her as Juno upon cloud.
我只哄自己的妻子 好久没见到她了
I would fall to my own wife, too long from my arms.
已经派人告诉科妮莉亚 说你推迟抵达
Cornelia has been sent word of your delay.
推迟
Delay?
我一路风尘仆仆赶过来 连澡都没顾得上洗
Is that what you term setting upon me as I return through city gate,
匆匆忙忙进了城 你就这么说我
in advance of bath or fresh robe to erase hard journey?
我说是必要的推迟
I term it necessity.
我们都知道你在国外打了胜仗
Your victories abroad are well known.
还有你的独断专行
As is your insolence
不等地方总督许可
in waging battle against the allies
与米特拉达梯的盟军大战一场
of Mithridates absent proconsuls' permission.
要是傻等那群糊涂蛋的指令
The province would have been lost
行省早就被夺走了
if I had waited on word from those sodden fools.
正如我要是等着你来
Ah, as I would've lost advantage of lone voice upon ear,
这儿就没我说话的地方了
if I had waited to break word with you.
有话直说
Speak plainly.
我讨厌绕弯子
I grow tired of mystery.
敞开天窗说亮话
Ah, then let us part veil.
你有恺撒家族的尊荣名号
You hold revered name of the Julian clan.
继承了维纳斯的血脉
Sired from the bloodline of Venus.
她是埃涅阿斯的圣母 尊贵的罗马缔造者
Divine mother of Aeneas, forbearer of Romulus,
罗穆卢斯的先祖
exalted founder of Rome
我那该死的家世背景不用你来教
I require no lesson in my fucking heritage.
那么就说说我的吧
Then perhaps one in mine.
我不是神明的后代
I am descendant from no god.
也没有显赫的头衔
Nor man of lofty note.
元老院之所以有我一席之地
I'm tolerated within the Senate
完全是因为我积累的雄厚财力
solely for the wealth I have amassed
那是我的劳动所得
through labor and dealings
是踩着那些有贵族血统的人爬上来的
those with "Proper" Lineage deem beneath them.
你认为这是他们讨厌你的唯一原因
And you believe this singular cause why they hate you, hmm?
你跟米特拉达梯的战斗
Your campaign against Mithridates
以及别的那些行动
and um other adventures.
很烧钱 对吧
Costly, were they not?
我知道你现在债台高累
I know you stand in considerable debt.
还有一群"糊涂蛋"视你为眼中钉
A dangerous place for a man to find himself,
恨不得除之而后快
when he's made enemies of the "Sodden fools"
你的处境可不妙
who would see him to ruin.
我会还清债务的
Ah, I shall see it repaid.
怎么还
By what means?
你有头衔却没有财富
You possess name absent wealth.
你有财富却没有头衔
And you possess wealth absent name.
如果克拉苏和恺撒联手
Imagine what could be wrested from highest perch,
何愁大事不成
were Crassus and Caesar to align themselves.
我自打出娘胎起
My name has remained constant
就背负起这名号了
since falling from my mother's womb.
你腰缠万贯也有这么多年了
You have been heavy with gold for equal years.
为何现在提出联手
Why now suggest the pairing?
因为攫取功名利禄的大好机会
Opportunity to seize laurels and the gratitude
摆到我们面前来了
of the Republic presents itself.
抓住机会 我们以后还能攫取更大的功名
And with it, first stone upon the road to greater glories.
那我要怎么帮助你
What would you have me aid you in,
才能早日看到这一天呢
to see such a day hastened?
平息奴隶叛乱
Bring end to slave rebellion.
杀死斯巴达克斯
And death of Spartacus.
埃提斯
Attius.
我找你有事 你这坏小子
I would have words, you fucking goat.
我操
Jupiter fuck me!
你疯了吗 怎么到这里来
Have you lost wit coming here, you mad shit?
你现在是罗马公敌
You are branded an enemy of Rome.
我听说你对共和国没什么好感
I was told you hold no love for the Republic.
别告诉我
Tell me you have not brought
你把携屎尿之使者带到我家里来了
the Bringer of Fucking Piss and Shit to my very door?
你是威名远扬啊
Your legend precedes you.
我带来的是机会
I bring but opportunity.
你说不定可以大赚一笔
One that you may profit greatly from,
只要你愿意
if you are of a mind.
那利润必须非常可观
It would have to be very considerable,
抵得上我受牵连的危险
to outweigh risk of association dragging me to depths.
该有的自然会有
A river shall flow in its wake,
只要我们达到了想要的目的
if we find ourselves lighted upon favorable shore.
你们冒险进来是为了什么
What would such a journey require?
你的本行 锻造兵器的技术
Your skill, towards the fashioning of swords.
兵器
Swords?
该死的市政官不准我锻造武器
The fucking Aedile denies me the crafting of weapons,
怕被你们这些造反的拿去
blame laid on fear of your rebellion.
现在只准打造工具
All that is struck now are fucking
还有镣铐
tools and shackles,
好让那些该死的权贵们控制奴隶
to keep the slaves of those privileged fucks in hand.
不用管市政官怎么想
The Aedile will not be of concern.
你们需要多少
How many would you need?
两把剑就行了
Two will see our needs met.
你们给的钱可远远不止买两把剑
You give coin enough for many times what you ask.
多的钱随你处置
The balance towards your discretion.
你们到底要干什么 搞得神秘兮兮的
And what purpose will silent tongue not speak of?
同意还是不同意
Do we have agreement?
两把剑 然后我们各不相干
Two swords, and an end to involvement.
日落时来拿
Return as sun falls.
我留在这儿
I would linger,
跟这位可信的朋友叙叙旧
and recall joyous times with trusted friend.
我不放心这个罗马人
I hold concern for the Roman.
希望那些钱足够让他乖乖办事
Let us hope the weight of coin anchors him to purpose.
如果他没这个狗胆呢
What if coward done more to him?
那他肯定被石头砸死
We shall see him dash upon rocks.
去跟艾力冈会合
Rejoin Agron.
做好准备
Make preparations.
月到中天 城门便会升起来
When moon is at its highest, we shall see gate raised.
这座城的劫数便要到了
And fucking city fall to deserved fate.
埃提斯
Attius.
我的胃口变大了
My appetite swells.
希留爱沙的城里面
Where would I find holdings of grain
哪儿有粮仓
within Sinuessa's walls?
质量上乘
The finest quality.
来自西西里岛的麦田
From the fields of Sicilia.
我有意大量购买
I have mind towards large acquisition.
我给你印上吧
Ah, I'll seal that for you.
抱歉
Apologies.
要等我夫君决定
My husband concludes business...
反正我白天也没有什么要紧事
No pressing concern until moon greets night.
你们的储量很足嘛
You stand well supplied.
今天刚从西西里岛运来一船货
Shipment received this day from Sicilia,
初一还有货运过来
with another to arrive upon the Kalends.
不过大部分都由克拉苏收购了
Although most of that has already been purchased by Crassus.
马科斯•克拉苏
Marcus Crassus?
我们的商铺是他最中意的
He favors our stores above all others.
而且因为斯巴达克斯的叛乱
And one of the few that can yet afford cost,
开销与日俱增 能承担的商铺也没几家了
ever rising in light of events concerning the rebel Spartacus.
我在旅途中也有所耳闻 他带来的麻烦不小
Have heard of the distress he has caused the Republic, in my travels.
你来希留爱沙山是为什么呢
What brings you to Sinuessa en Valle?
奴隶
Slaves.
我身边的奴隶不断增多
I find myself with ever expanding family of them,
希望保证他们吃饱穿暖
and would ensure they are well provided for.
你打算让他们住在城里
You have thought toward housing them in the city?
有这样想过
It has crossed mind.
如果你希望他们过上舒服日子
If you wish to see them any form of comfort,
我劝你打消这个念头
I would strike from such.
我看到有个奴隶在市场上被砸死了
I witnessed a slave stoned in the marketplace.
很常见吗
A common occurrence?
不
No.
但恐怕以后就常见了
Yet I fear it will become so,
如果叛乱的事情不能很快解决的话
if this matter of rebellion is not soon concluded.
那我们祈祷吧
Let us pray, then.
希望有个好的结局
For the proper end to it.
他终于忙完了
He at last frees himself.
你今早在现场观刑吧
You were at the stoning this morning, were you not?
我参与了一起不幸的事件
I was present at unfortunate spectacle.
然后早早地结束了刑罚
And ended it prematurely.
多谢
Gratitude.
人们的情绪几近疯狂
The crowd pressed towards frenzy.
我不想再看到无谓的流血
I would not see more blood spilled absent cause.
我也一样
Nor I.
不要无谓的流血
Absent cause.
拿刀替我修面
Bring knife to bear upon beard.
为什么不听从指令
Why do you pause in the face of command?
她只不过听从更高的指令
She but obeys a higher one.
主人命令你不得修面
The dominus orders you to remain unshorn.
为了什么
Toward what purpose?
他的想法只有他本人知道
His thoughts are his own in such regard.
那你的呢
And what are yours?
我不明白
I do not understand.
这是个很简单的问题
It is a simple question.
你是怎么想的呢
What are your thoughts?
想什么
Towards what subject?
站在你面前的这个人
The one that stands before you.
你认为恺撒这人怎样
How do you gauge Caesar?
我不认识他
I do not know him,
说不出有用的观点
and can form no opinion of worth.
无论问什么
Demand any question,
他都会如实相告
and he shall break answer to aid you.
你不是有妇之夫吗
You are taken with wife?
你的眼睛很像我妻子的
Your eyes stand as my wife's.
唇齿的味道也是一样
As does taste upon lips.
温柔的抚摸能让我想起她
I would be reminded of her in shadow's touch.
眼睛闭上便没什么不同
Eyes shut towards difference...
让热切的记忆温暖我的身心
and warmed by longing remembrance...
克芮
Kore.
离开这里
Remove yourself.
遵命 主人
Yes, Dominus.
你送来了好酒与美人
You send gift of wine and warm embrace,
却又抢走…
only to snatch away
她不是用来满足你的兽欲的
She was not sent for your fucking pleasure.
抱歉
Apologies.
我以为那女人无足轻重
I did not know the girl held meaning.
你在外征战太久 放荡惯了
You've been away too long from civilized company.
穿好袍子
See yourself to robe,
把心思放到更要紧的事情上
and thoughts towards more pressing matters.
你向他袒胸露乳
You present yourself with breasts and ass
尽显曼妙身姿
formed with morning dew.
他这样欲火旺盛的男人
Is it wonder that a man strong of desire
当然蠢蠢欲动 想要尝尝鲜了
would not be tempted to taste such ripe offering?
吸取教训 给我滚出去
Take lesson and remove yourself from fucking sight.
遵命 女主人
Yes, Domina.
我们还没有足够的马匹
We have not yet procured enough horses.
我不希望看到骑兵在关键时刻不够用
I will not have cavalry found lacking in moment of need.
出什么事了
What has happened?
没什么事 抱歉
Nothing of concern, apologies.
说出来 我给你做主
Break words, and find comfort in how they are received.
我刚才奉命伺候恺撒
I was attending Caesar as commanded...
恺撒
Caesar?
盖乌斯•尤利乌斯•恺撒
Gaius Julius Caesar?
他对我动手动脚
He laid hands upon me.
要不是你父亲出现 我…
If your father had not appeared, I...
他在哪儿
Where is he?
我们所追捕的人
The man we hunt...
曾是竞技场的冠军
was a champion at the arena,
作战的本事不逊于任何人
to rival any in the Republic.
他再厉害 也就是个角斗士
Yet only a gladiator, regardless of skill.
他是如何击败罗马军团的
How has he bested our legions?
斯巴达克斯熟知战争
Spartacus knows of war,
从他在色雷斯的时候起就开始征战了
and the waging of it from his days in Thrace.
如果传言是真的
If rumor is true,
格雷博那个蠢货在死于维苏威一役之前
he fought among the auxiliary beneath the fool Glaber
斯巴达克斯在他的辅军中战斗过
before his fall of Vesuvius.
这么说他对我们的战术也很熟悉了
Then he's familiar with our tactics.
并且利用这些知识 摧毁那些曾压迫他的人
And has used such knowledge to the regret of those that have pressed him.
他自以为熟悉罗马战士的套路
He believes he knows what a "Proper" Roman soldier will do.
我们可以利用这一点
A thing that could be turned toward advantage.
真希望我的孩子有这样的头脑
Would that my own blood stood now so sharp of mind.
多经历战火的淬炼
Ah, years and the taste of battle
你那乖乖狗自然能牙尖爪利
will hone your pup's teeth.
这点我倒从不怀疑
Of that I have little doubt.
但要击败斯巴达克斯 我需要不是狗而是狼
Yet to bring Spartacus to ground I must have a wolf at my side.
那我们便在月圆之夜亮出尖牙 仰天长嗥
And let us turn gleaming fang towards moon of full purpose,
杀他个血肉横飞
and see blood and gore matted upon fur.
宵禁 不准外出
Curfew! Inside please.
全都进屋子
Make your way indoors!
宵禁 快走快走
Curfew! Move, move.
快走
Move along!
不准在街上逗留
Off the streets!
快离开
You move along!
街上不准留人
Clear these streets!
梅莎莉娜
Messalina!
这孩子就是喜欢胡闹
She has a habit of running wild.
给
Here.
不要离开你母亲身边
You stay close to your mother.
多谢
Gratitude.
快进去
You inside.
站住
You there.
今天早上在广场我就注意你了
I laid eyes upon you in the square this morning,
- 是你吧 - 彼此彼此
- did I not? - As I upon you.
听说你早上在城门口
Word has reached ear you spoke my name
搬出我的名号 说是要找我有事
upon entering gate, claiming business.
恐怕你是搞错了
I fear you have been misled.
你还不值得我浪费时间
You have nothing I find of worth.
那你进城是为了什么
Then why are you within these walls?
松手
Remove hand.
到底是干什么
What is your purpose here?
你去问我夫君 自然就有答案了
Put question to honored husband, and have reply.
他和市政官做生意吗
He trades with the Aedile?
是的
He does.
那就是我误会了
The mistake is mine, then.
天黑后不要到处乱晃
See yourself from the streets before nightfall,
不要让我再误会你
to avoid further misunderstanding.
走
Come along!
抱歉
Apologies.
并不是城里的每个人都像他这样
I assure you, not all in the city stand as him.
他说要我别到处乱晃
What he spoke of, removing myself from the streets...?
很讨厌吧
Is it not troublesome?
我也劝过我夫君
I made attempt to dissuade my husband,
但他觉得在彻底平叛之前
but he thought it best to have streets cleared
最好是清空街道
of all but city guard,
只留下卫兵巡逻
until the rebellion has been quelled.
你有地方过夜吗
You have a place to call your own this night?
有
Yes.
我正要过去呢
I have my eye towards such.
都进去
Move inside!
清空所有街道
All streets are to be cleared!
宵禁开始
Curfew is in affect!
加强戒备
A little more securer this time!
卫兵清空了街道
The streets cleared by guards?
是市政官的命令
By command of the Aedile.
你知道吗
Did you know of this?
去你妈的
Fuck yourself.
我又不比别人多知道什么
News greets me with shared ear.
相信能满足你们的要求
Trust these will service need.
肯定能
They will.
不过我们现在还有要求
Yet there is more we must ask of you now.
我就知道
I thought as much.
两百第纳尔
Two hundred denarii a piece,
你可以在这里过夜
and you may lay hidden here until sun crests
直到解除宵禁
and curfew is lifted.
我没打算过夜
It is not sleep we seek.
你以为我脑子抽风了吗
What deformity of mind do you think I suffer from,
还要继续跟罗马公敌合作
that I would give further aid to enemies of Rome?
你对共和国又没什么感情
You hold no love of the republic.
酒灌多了吧 你也多愁善感起来了
Sentiment often through wine so in years past.
至少我有吃有喝 有别人羡慕的特权
Words of the drunk and food, jealous of privilege.
我们正巧钱多得使不完
We find ourselves heavy with Roman coin.
你开个价吧
What cost would sober intent?
五千第纳尔应该足够我离开这座城
Five thousand denarii would see me far from this city,
离开天杀的罗马了
and shores of fucking Republic.
成交
A bargain well struck.
老子不再是罗马人了
Call me Roman no more, then!
你要多少剑
How many more swords do you need?
足够装备那些加入我们的人
Those that join us are well armed.
加入你们
Join you?
你们想要攻占这座城吗
You move to take the fucking city?!
是解放它
We move to liberate it.
唯一阻挡我们的是城门
The gate stands only in our path.
我们本打算趁夜偷袭 打开城门
We would to slit throats in the night and see it raised.
却没预料到宵禁
Unexpected curfew presents difficulty
这就很难隐秘行动了
in reaching it unnoticed.
卫兵看到我们就会大叫大喊
City guard would raise clamor well in advance
这我可帮不上忙
I cannot aid you in this.
小命都保不住
It would mean my life.
你已经亲手为斯巴达克斯打了一把剑
You have forged weapons for Spartacus himself.
只要他们发现我们手中拿着你的剑
If we are discovered with your craft clutched in hand,
你跟不跟我们干也都是一个死
then they will send you to the afterlife all the same.
操他妈的
Fuck the gods.
你要我怎么做
What would you have of me?
轻一点
Gently.
别笨手笨脚的弄坏了里面的东西
I should not have content fall to ruin by rough use.
把剩下的都搬过来
Go fetch the rest.
要他们搬的时候当心
See that they are careful.
这些不必要的东西可都是我行军的累赘
You would see me weighted with unnecessary comforts.
我有那么重吗
Have I grown that heavy?
这是你的东西
These are yours?
如果战事拖太久
I would not be found wanting,
我可不希望独守空房 害你空想
if campaign stretches beyond expectation.
你想随我去跟斯巴达克斯打仗吗
You wish to join me, in pursuit of Spartacus?
我可不想
I wish no such thing.
但我更不想几个月甚至几年
Yet I will not be removed from your arms
不在你身边
for months threatening years.
普布利乌斯和我要陪你和提比略一起去
Publius and I shall travel with you and Tiberius.
你知道军营里是不能有女人的
You know women are forbidden within encampment.
但没有规定女人不能进侍从营地
Yet they are not banned from followers' camp,
除非我连规矩改了都不知道
unless rules have shifted absent knowledge.
我不允许家人睡在奴隶和妓女当中
I would not have my family bedded among slaves and whores.
即便如此
Is it not better solution
也好过留他们在千里之外
than having them stricken from embrace?
你的心意我领了
Desire much appreciated.
但如此靠近敌人 我必会分神
Yet I could not stay mind from thought of your safety,
担忧你的安全
placed so near the enemy.
我要你留在这里
I would have you remain here,
远离随时能取人性命的战争
far from the threat of death war so often promises.
只是这样吗
Is that sole reason?
父亲
Father.
一切已就绪
All has been attended.
您的军队已准备好 天亮就启程
Your army stands ready to march upon first light.
很好
News well received.
我还有话说
I would have word.
唯一的问题就是我的头衔
There yet lingers issue of what title I shall hold.
我正在考虑这样的问题
I am possessed of leanings towards the matter.
日出时分自有定论
Morning sun shall see them fall to place.
把这些东西都放回去
Have these returned from where they sprang.
我出发之前 要看到这里井然有序
I would have house in order before we take leave from it.
我以为荣耀的职位只属于我
I thought honored position all but mine.
现在恐怕他另有人选
Now I fear he favors another.
那你跟母亲一样了
Then you stand as your mother,
只有血缘维系 却是无足轻重
bound by blood and inconsiderate worth.
非常精美
It is a thing of rare beauty.
对吧
Is it not?
是 主人
Yes, Dominus.
您征讨斯巴达克斯时会佩带吗
You will carry it when you face Spartacus?
我要带父亲的剑
I shall carry my father's sword.
虽然没有这把剑精美绝伦
It is not as well bred or considered as this...
却有更深的意义
yet it holds deeper meaning.
那么由恺撒佩带吗
Caesar will carry it then?
代您行使权力
As your word and will?
我不该让你离他这么近
I should not have placed you within his reach.
他的原始欲望很强烈
He is a man of base needs.
那为何给他的头衔 高过您的儿子
Then why honor him with title, that above your son?
抱歉 我冒犯了
Apologies, I overstep.
你只是说出了心里话
You speak your heart.
我知道你关心那小子
I know your concern for the boy.
他已经不是孩子
He no longer stands as such.
不过在父亲眼里还是
But in the eyes of his father.
真希望我妻子也能说出这般话来
Would my wife could voice such simple wisdom.
我看到了那些行李
I saw the gathering of trunks.
她跟随您一同去吗
She goes with you?
她这样要求
It was her intent.
但我在她身上找不到安慰
Yet I would find no comfort in her presence.
而你可以给我
As I would in yours...
真的可以吗
Is such a thing possible?
虽然我只能让你住在侍从营地
I will be forced to place you within followers' camp.
但这是真的
But yes, it is possible.
如果你也愿意
If you so desire it.
愿意 主人
Yes, Dominus.
我并非以主人身份提问
I do not pose question as master,
而是以一个男人
but as a man.
所以请你回答一个男人的提问
And would have answer as one.
愿意
Yes.
我希望如此 马科斯
It is something I desire, Marcus.
我操
Fuck my ass...
快
Quickly!
我们要召集人手 拿起武器
We must gather more men and swords!
斯巴达克斯在这里
Spartacus is here!
没时间了 他到底搞定了没有
There is no more time. What did it come of him?
想搞清楚只有一个办法
There is one way to know.
那我们便去搞清楚吧
Let us see it done or wrong.
月亮升到顶了
The moon nears its peak.
该死的城门还关得那么死
Yet fucking gate stands firmly rooted.
他们肯定能打开
They will see it raised.
要么死在城门下
Or fall in attempt.
让大家准备
Ready the others.
城门一动 就是杀人见血的时候
When gate trembles, death follows upon heel.
斯巴达克斯在城内
Spartacus is within our walls!
行动 跟我来
Move, come with me.
把城门看紧
See gate protected!
你去打开库房
You, open the storeroom!
快
Quickly!
这事情少不了你的奖赏
Reward will surely find hands for this.
那是毫无疑问的
Of that I have no fucking doubt.
- 埃提斯 - 发警报
- Attius! - Raise the alarm
去喊人
Call for more men!
躲起来 完事了我去找你
Hide yourself, I will find you when it is over!
把门打开
See gate opened!
干掉他们
Clear the way!
行动
Move!
拿起武器
Arm yourselves!
去前门
Forward towards the front gate!
迪欧特莫斯
Diotimus.
洛厄斯呢
Where is Laurus?
我在这里 奴隶
I am here, slave.
你们要背叛主人 参加叛军吗
You would turn against your dominus and join rebellion?
该死的畜生
Fucking animals...
迪欧特莫斯
Diotimus.
宅子已拿下
The villa is taken.
你们快解开
See yourselves free.
快走
Move.
我主人
My dominus...
死了吗
He is dead?
那我就跟他一起去黄泉
Then I shall follow him to the afterlife...
朝他的鬼魂撒泡尿
and piss upon his shadow...
乌尔比安
Ulpianus!
我们要逃去米利亚峰
We flee to Melia Ridge,
趁他们还没有封锁退路
if they have not already sealed escape.
你们见到我夫君了吗
Have you seen my husband...?
没有 我们必须走了
I have not, we must go.
我找到他就去追你们
I will follow once I find him.
愿诸神保佑你
May the gods protect you.
市政官呢
The Aedile.
你见过市政官吗
Have you seen the Aedile?
是你
You.
你是斯巴达克斯的帮凶
You aid Spartacus?
不
No.
我就是他本人
I stand the man himself.
恺撒
Caesar.
我还以为是克拉苏呢
I had thought to find Crassus himself,
语调一模一样
the tone so matching.
我很骄傲能像我父亲
I am proud reflection of my father.
你是提比略
Tiberius?
真他妈操蛋
Jupiter's fucking cock,
上次见你 你还是个孩子
you were but a child since I last laid eyes.
抱歉
Apologies.
出发前我要回一趟家
I am for my own home before we march,
我不想因为这事弄脏了家里
I did not wish to stain it with such business.
出国多年怎么让你养成这种怪癖
Years abroad led you to strange pleasures,
倒是很符合你野蛮的形象
worthy of the beast you appear.
你父亲…没有给你说过吗
And your father... he's not spoken to you of this?
他要思考更紧迫的事情
He finds himself preoccupied with more pressing concerns.
他迟早会信任你的
Well, I'm certain he will share confidence.
等他认为你配得上的时候
When he deems you deserving.
你觉得我不配吗
You think I am not?
睡个好觉 小少爷
Sleep well, young master.
到梦里体会未来的荣耀吧
And dream of future glories.
在我的指挥下
Under my command.
赛纳斯
Sanus.
求你了 别杀我妻子
Please, let my wife live!
我们已经拿下这座城
The city is taken.
把幸存的罗马人都锁起来
See the Romans that yet live to chains.
锁起来
Chains?
你留他们的狗命
You let them live?
他们没有威胁
They pose no threat.
也屁用没有
Nor fucking use.
如果换成我们求饶 他们会开恩吗
Would they show mercy if we were beneath heel?
别动 混蛋
Still, cunt!
斯巴达克斯
Spartacus!
市政官把自己关在粮仓里
The Aedile bars himself in the horreum,
泼满了沥青 还扬言要点燃
spilling pitch and threatens to put light to bear.
过来
Come.
我绝不帮你们这些畜生
I will not lend aid to you and your animals.
如果粮食都被烧了
If grain is put to fire,
连我都没办法管住那些"畜生"了
even I will not have voice to calm my "Animals."
你必须这样做
You will do this,
不然那些幸存的人绝对没有活路
or see your people that yet live fall from this world.
- 饶命 - 别动
- Please. - Stay still!
你们休想得到这座城
You will not have my city's heart!
杀了他们
Kill them!
杀了他们 操翻罗马人
Kill them! Fuck the Roman man!
谁敢走近 我就丢火把
Make attempt on gate and I will for all to torch,
该死的混蛋
you fucking cunts!
我可以解决他
I can take him...
艾力冈
Agron!
放下矛
Lower spear.
莱塔
Laeta...
全部杀光
Kill them all!
过去
Go to him.
祈祷他能听你的话
And pray your words hold meaning.
别听他的话
Don't listen to his words!
就是他让我们受苦的
He's the reason we suffered!
我以为你死了
I thought you dead.
你把我们的命运交到她手里
You would place our fate in her fucking hands.
我自有主意
I place it in what I believe in.
我活着 还有一些人活着
I yet live, among a clutch of others.
多少
How many?
很少
Too few.
如果你不住手 活着的就更少了
And we will be fewer still, if you do not stop this.
我们辛苦挣来的一切就拱手相让吗
You would give them all we have worked for?
今夜我看了太多流血死亡
I would see no more death this night.
打开门 让我们看到明天的太阳升起
Open gate, let us see sun crest upon another day.
我绝不向奴隶低头
I will not bow to fucking slaves!
别老想着他们 想想你的人民
Turn thought from them, and towards your people.
你要是不住手
If you do this,
黄泉之下你如何向他们交代
you will condemn them all to the afterlife.
包括我在内
Your wife among them...
不要
Oh, no!
他会开门的
He would have opened the gate!
他一定会的
I know he would of.
他会为了我打开门的
He would have opened the gate for me.
我不能押在他身上
I could not place faith in it.
今晚我们杀够了 也报了仇
We have had our fill of blood and vengeance this night.
不要再残害幸存的罗马人
No Roman that yet draws breath shall suffer further harm.
这座城是我们的了
The city is ours!
我们自由了
The city is free!
罗马人又一次失败了
Once again the Romans fall!
胜利
Victory!
看到心爱的人死去是难以承受的痛
To see one loved robbed of life is a heavy thing.
但罗马人不止一次这样伤害我
One done lightly by Romans many times to me.
也许无法安慰你
It is no balm,
但请记住 你所有的痛都压在我的肩上
but know that I carry the full weight of your loss.
把她锁起来
Place her in chains.
有战争就会有牺牲
War often carries with it great sacrifice.
没有什么比
None more keenly felt
至爱的亲人离开这个世界
than threat of those one holds closest to heart
更让人难过的了
struck from this world.
我不要我的儿子落到这样的结局
I would not have my son fall to such a fate
在他还不能胜任指挥官的时候
because he was not ready for command.
我也不能拒绝给他机会
Nor would I deny him opportunity,
让他向父亲证明自己长大成人
to prove himself a man in his father's eyes.
你代我行使权力
You stand as my word and my will.
受您重托 父亲
You honor me, father.
我绝对不辱克拉苏家族之名
As I shall honor the name of Crassus.
跟恺撒同行 带上你挑选的人
Ride with Caesar and men of your choosing.
去找莫姆缪斯以及科西尼斯的残军
Seek out Mummius and what remains of Cossinius' legion.
找到斯巴达克斯 汇报他的动向
Find Spartacus and send word of his movement,
但不要打草惊蛇
but do not tempt engagement
等我带主力部队到达
until I have arrived with proper force.
你信誓旦旦 说得天花乱坠
You fill the air with lofty promise,
就是为了让我听命于一个小毛孩
only to command I bow to a fucking boy?!
他是我儿子
He is my son!
你既然尊重我 也应该尊重他
And shall be treated with mirrored respect!
我为你担任军事保民官一职花了不少钱
I have spread coin towards your election as Military Tribune.
提比略还太年轻 不足冠以正式头衔
Formal title Tiberius is yet too young to hold.
带上我的徽章 你可以自由出入军营
Wear my token to pass unmolested through encampment,
直到显露你的真实身份
until appearance is shorn to Roman likeness.
我更喜欢那把剑和期望的职位
I would prefer fancy sword and expected position.
按我指给你的路走
Stay upon path I have set,
路到尽头 你自然荣耀加身
and see greater glories bestowed at journey's end.
吹响号角
Sound horn!
我们往南征讨斯巴达克斯叛军
We advance south on Spartacus and those who follow him in rebellion!
让倒向叛军的乱臣贼子
Let our shadow fall upon them...
不分男女老幼
and every man, woman, and child
在罗马的荣光与威力之下
so touched by it struck from this world
死无葬身之地
by the might and glory of Rome!